Preliminary Guide to the Benjamin Franklin University records, 1925-1994 RG0116
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Benjamin Franklin University records
1925-1994
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
RG0116
73.75 Linear Feet
This collection contains course catalogs, yearbooks, student grades, course books, photographs, brochures, handbooks, and commencement programs. They range in date from 1925 to 1994.
Restrictions on Access
Series 1 is closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.. Series 3 is closed to research for 50 years from date of record creation except for yearbooks, bulletins, and catalogs.
Acquisition Information
The collection was transferred to the University Archives of the Special Collections Department in 1988 by the Office of the President and Office of the Provost when the school merged with The George Washington University. A second transfer occured in 1994 by the Office of the President and Office of the Provost.
Historical or Biographical Note
Benjamin Franklin University, formerly Pace Institute, merged with The George Washington University in 1987 within the School of Business and Public Management.
In 1907, Homer S. Pace established the Washington Branch of Pace Institute, offering the first professional accounting courses in the District of Columbia. Pace, noted for composing the definition of Accountancy, established the school to primarily meet the needs of the part-time student. For some nine years, Pace Institute offered the only available accounting courses in Washington, D.C.
In 1925, Benjamin Franklin University was organized and incorporated to succeed Pace Institute. The Founder and President, John Thomas Kennedy, established the University as a continuation of the Pace courses to provide the part-time student with a professional education in Accountancy, Financial Administration and General Business. Kennedy, a fourth generation Philadelphian, was a staunch admirer of the principles of thrift and self-reliance advocated by Benjamin Franklin and thus named the University after the fellow-Philadelphian.
In its charter, the University was authorized to confer Academic Degrees for both undergraduate and post-graduate work. Under the Act of March 2, 1929, Benjamin Franklin University was licensed by the District of Columbia Board of Education to confer the Associate in Business Administration, the Bachelor of Commercial Science and the Master of Commercial Science.
The faculty consisted of men whose success in the practice of accountancy, auditing, law and taxation was widely recognized. The graduates distinguished themselves in the field of Accountancy and accomplished many notable "firsts" in the United States. From 1925 to 1938, the University offered its day and evening courses in the Department of Transportation. On January 1, 1938, the University moved to 1100 Sixteenth Street, just four blocks north of the White House grounds. By the 1980s Benjamin Franklin University offered the Associate, Bachelor, and Master's Degrees in the fields of Accountancy and Financial Management.
In 1987, an agreement was signed that merged Benjamin Franklin University and The George Washington University. President Lloyd Elliott stated that "The agreement provides an excellent opportunity for qualified Benjamin Franklin University students to continue their education." In 1992, the Benjamin Franklin Chair was established in the School of Business and Public Management.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains course catalogs, yearbooks, student grades, course books, photographs, brochures, handbooks, and commencement programs. They range in date from 1925 to 1994. The collection was transferred to the University Archives of the Special Collections Department in 1988 by the Office of the President and Office of the Provost when the school merged with The George Washington University. A second transfer occured in 1994 by the Office of the President and Office of the Provost.
NOTE: University Archives does not maintain BFU student transcripts. Contact the GW Office of the Registrar.
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: Print materials; Photographs; Departmental files; and History and programs.
Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Washington (D.C.); Photographs; George Washington University; George Washington University. School of Business; Pace, Homer St. Clair; Kennedy, John Thomas; Benjamin Franklin University; Elliott, Lloyd H.
- Print materials, 1925-1987; RG0116 Series 1; 21 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is a collection of Benjamin Franklin University files, accreditation materials, exams, and proctor sheets. The dates range from 1925 to 1987.
  Formerly ACC#3
  This series has a container list in electronic form, please ask staff for assistance.
- Photographs, 1925-1987; RG0116 Series 2; 8 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 11, Box 10, Box 9, Box 8, Box 7, Box 14, Box 15, Box 12, Box 13)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  One folder "Faculty and Class images, 1941" in box 7 was a gift of Ellen Travis Perry, March 3, 2011 (2011.025)
  This series is a collection of photographs that are divided into three subseries of the following topics: graduating class, individuals, and special events. The dates of the photographs range from 1925 to 1987.
- Departmental files, 1925-1987; RG0116 Series 3; 44.5 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30)
  This series is a collection of Benjamin Franklin University brochures, pamphlets, course catalogs, yearbooks, alumni bulletins, treasurer's files, accounting files, 1987 graduation papers, student grades, as well as course books covering law, business, and accounting. The items range from 1925 to 1987.
  Formerly ACC#215
  - Accreditation Standards, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accreditation Standards - auditing, attestation, criteria, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Admissions Office - form letter to prospective students and application, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alumni- biographies/news clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alumni Association - directory, newsletters, applications, etc., 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - BFU Student handbook, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - BFU Undergraduate Almanack - background and course descriptions, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brochures, 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Commencement - invitations, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Day Division - brochures, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Day & Evening Divisions - brochures, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Evening Division - brochures, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Federal Financial Aid - guide & application, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Graduate Programs - brochures, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Graduate School Schedules, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Graduates passing Certified Public Accountant exam, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - M.B.A Program brochures, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - National Association of Accountants -Washington Chapter roster, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Placement Office - applicants for student assistance, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pullman Company stock - copy of shares held by BFU, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Schedules, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - BFU bound catalogs, 1925-1937 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - BFU bound catalogs, 1938-1948 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - BFU bound catalogs, 1948-1956 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - BFU bound catalogs, 1957-1965 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - BFU catalog, 1952-1953 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    General note
    Bound catalog
  - BFU catalog, 1953-1954 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - BFU catalog, 1955-1956 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    Bound catalog, two copies
  - BFU catalog, 1956-1957 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - BFU catalog, 1957-1958 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - BFU catalog, 1958-1959 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - BFU catalog, 1959-1960 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - BFU catalog, 1960-1961 (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - BFU catalog, 1961-1962 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    Bound catalog, three copies
  - BFU catalog, 1962-1963 (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - BFU catalog, 1963-1964 (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - BFU catalog, 1964-1965 (Box 29, Folder 12)
  - BFU catalog, 1965-1966 (Box 29, Folder 13)
  - BFU catalog, 1966-1967 (Box 29, Folder 14)
  - BFU catalog, 1967-1968 (Box 29, Folder 15)
  - BFU catalog, 1968-1969 (Box 29, Folder 16)
  - BFU catalog, 1969-1970 (Box 29, Folder 17)
  - BFU catalog, 1970-1971 (Box 29, Folder 18)
  - BFU catalog, 1971-1972 (Box 29, Folder 19)
  - BFU catalog, 1972-1973 (Box 29, Folder 20)
  - BFU catalog, 1973-1974 (Box 29, Folder 21)
  - BFU catalog, 1974-1975 (Box 29, Folder 22)
    Bound catalog, four copies
  - BFU catalog, 1975-1976 (Box 29, Folder 23)
  - BFU catalog, 1976-1977 (Box 29, Folder 24)
  - BFU catalog, 1978-1979 (Box 29, Folder 25)
  - BFU catalog, 1979-1980 (Box 29, Folder 26)
  - BFU catalog, 1980 (Box 29, Folder 27)
    Bound catalog, six copies
  - BFU catalog, 1981-1982 (Box 29, Folder 28)
  - BFU catalog, 1983 (Box 29, Folder 29)
  - BFU catalog, 1983-1984 (Box 29, Folder 30)
  - BFU catalog, 1984 (Box 29, Folder 31)
  - BFU catalog, 1984-1985 (Box 29, Folder 32)
  - BFU catalog, 1985 (Box 29, Folder 33)
    Bound catalog, five copies
  - BFU catalog, 1986-1987 (Box 29, Folder 34)
  - BFU catalog, 1987 (Box 29, Folder 35)
  - BFU Faculty Handbook, 1986-1987 (Box 29, Folder 36)
  - BFU Staff Handbook, 1986 (Box 29, Folder 37)
  - BFU Key, 1941 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - BFU Key, 1942 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - BFU Key, 1943 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - BFU Key, 1944 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - BFU Key, 1945 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - BFU Key, 1946 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - BFU Key, 1947 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - BFU Key, 1948 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    Two copies
  - BFU Key, 1949 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - BFU Key, 1950 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - BFU Key, 1951 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - BFU Key, 1952 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  - BFU Key, 1953 (Box 30, Folder 13)
  - BFU Key, 1954 (Box 30, Folder 14)
  - BFU Key, 1955 (Box 30, Folder 15)
  - BFU Key, 1960 (Box 30, Folder 16)
  - BFU Key, 1961 (Box 30, Folder 17)
  - BFU Key, 1962 (Box 30, Folder 18)
  - BFU Key, 1963 (Box 30, Folder 19)
  - BFU Key, 1964 (Box 30, Folder 20)
  - BFU Key, 1965 (Box 30, Folder 21)
  - BFU Key, 1967 (Box 30, Folder 22)
    Four copies
  - BFU Key, 1968 (Box 30, Folder 23)
  - BFU Key, 1969 (Box 30, Folder 24)
  - BFU Key, 1970 (Box 30, Folder 25)
  - BFU Key, 1971 (Box 30, Folder 26)
  - BFU Key, 1972 (Box 30, Folder 27)
  - BFU Key, 1973 (Box 30, Folder 28)
  - BFU Key, 1974 (Box 30, Folder 29)
  - BFU Key, 1975-1976 (Box 30, Folder 30)
  - BFU Key, 1976-1977 (Box 30, Folder 31)
  - BFU Key, 1977-1978 (Box 30, Folder 32)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1940 (Box 30, Folder 33)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1952 (Box 30, Folder 34)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1953 (Box 30, Folder 35)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1957 (Box 30, Folder 36)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1958 (Box 30, Folder 37)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1959 (Box 30, Folder 38)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1960 (Box 30, Folder 39)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1961 (Box 30, Folder 40)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1962 (Box 30, Folder 41)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1963 (Box 30, Folder 42)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1965 (Box 30, Folder 43)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1966 (Box 30, Folder 44)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1967 (Box 30, Folder 45)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1968 (Box 30, Folder 46)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1974 (Box 30, Folder 47)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1975 (Box 30, Folder 48)
    Three copies
  - BFU Commencement program, 1976 (Box 30, Folder 49)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1977 (Box 30, Folder 50)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1978 (Box 30, Folder 51)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1979 (Box 30, Folder 52)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1981 (Box 30, Folder 53)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1982 (Box 30, Folder 54)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1983 (Box 30, Folder 55)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1984 (Box 30, Folder 56)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1986 (Box 30, Folder 57)
  - BFU Commencement program, 1987 (Box 30, Folder 58)
  - BFU Photographs, Faculty and Classes of 1928 (Map-folder 1)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates of 1933 (Map-folder 2)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1934 (Map-folder 3)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates of 1935 (Map-folder 4)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates 1937 (Map-folder 5)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates 1940 (Map-folder 6)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates 1941 (Map-folder 7)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates 1942 (Map-folder 8)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates 1943 (Map-folder 9)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates 1944 (Map-folder 10)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates 1945 (Map-folder 11)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates 1946 (Map-folder 12)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates 1947 (Map-folder 13)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates 1948 (Map-folder 14)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates 1949 (Map-folder 15)
  - BFU Photographs, Graduates 1950 (Map-folder 16)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1952 (Map-folder 17)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1953 (Map-folder 18)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1954 (Map-folder 19)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1955 (Map-folder 20)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1956 (Map-folder 21)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1957 (Map-folder 22)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1958 (Map-folder 23)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1959 (Map-folder 24)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1960 (Map-folder 25)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1961 (Map-folder 26)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1962 (Map-folder 27)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1963 (Map-folder 28)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1964 (Map-folder 29)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1965 (Map-folder 30)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1966 (Map-folder 31)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1967 (Map-folder 32)
  - BFU Photographs, Class of 1968 (Map-folder 33)
- History and programs, 1977-1994; RG0116 Series 4; .25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series includes histories, correspondence, programs, musical score, and a student thesis. They range in date from 1977-94.
  Formerly vertical files
  - Benjamin Franklin University, 1978 ca.-1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Franklin University - Student Thesis (1977), 1977-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)